<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some remarks upon the life of that painful servant of God, Mr. Nathanael Heywood minister of the Gospel of Christ ... who died in the 44th year of his age ... / by Sir H. Ashurst.</title>
            <author>Ashurst, Henry, 1614?-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15202863</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15202863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1139:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some remarks upon the life of that painful servant of God, Mr. Nathanael Heywood minister of the Gospel of Christ ... who died in the 44th year of his age ... / by Sir H. Ashurst.</title>
                  <author>Ashurst, Henry, 1614?-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], x, 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Cockerill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The life and death of Mr. Nathanael Heywood.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heywood, Nathaniel, 1633-1677.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME REMARKS UPON THE LIFE Of that Painful Servant of God Mr. <hi>Nathanael Heywood,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt at <hi>Ormeskirk</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi> Who Died in the 44th Year of his Age. Dedicated to the Right Honourable HUGH Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> by Sir <hi>H. Aſhhurſt,</hi> Bar<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> over-againſt <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103239:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103239:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable HUGH Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Baron of PARHAM.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Take the boldneſs to Dedicate to Your Lordſhip ſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs of the Life of an Excellent Perſon, who was Your Country-man, and
<pb facs="tcp:103239:3"/> one for whom Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip had a juſt eſteem. It is not to recommend to Your Lordſhip any <hi>Party</hi> of men among us, but <hi>plain Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi> in Legible and Lively Characters; and to remove a Common Objection againſt the moſt Excellent Precepts of our Bleſſed Saviour, that they are <hi>hard Sayings,</hi> and <hi>impracticable things.</hi> Here, in a very plain manner, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to Your view a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Jeſus Chriſt, who had no other Deſign in the World, but that of <hi>doing good</hi> to Mankind, and is now partaking of the Eternal Joy of his Lord and Maſter, to
<pb facs="tcp:103239:3"/> whom he was ſo entirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted.</p>
            <p>It is Your Lordſhip's Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Ancient and Noble Extraction that ſets You a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the common Level of Mankind, and draws the Eyes of the World upon You; but there is ſomewhat greater, Your Exemplary Piety and Zeal for our Holy Religion (in ſuch a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and licentious Age) and the Countenance you give to Serious Piety, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you find it among all the different Parties that we are ſo unhappily broken into, that makes you the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:103239:4"/> of Your Country, and highly eſteemed by Wiſe and Good Men, and obliges me to be with all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt Humble and Faithful Servant, <hi>H. ASHHURST.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:103239:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE great God is greatly ſeen in the ſmalleſt things; a poor Sparrow lighting on the earth, and a minute Hair of mens Heads, are concerned by the Omnipotent Providence: How much more doth the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Jehovah</hi> order the Affairs of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men, and moſt of all the Concerns of his Church, which is the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> the inmoſt Circle of Divine Providence: It is congruous to the Church's ſtate in this world to be Militant; a Lilly among Thorns: Her Husband was a Man of Sorrows, and it becomes not his Bride to be a Wife of Pleaſures: If the Head was <note place="margin">Non opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet membra deliciari ſub capite ſpinis coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato.</note> crown'd with Thorns, the Members muſt not think much to be conformable: <hi>If they do theſe things to the green tree, what will they do to the dry?</hi> Nay, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:103239:5"/> and ſalutiferous for this Body to be purged: This Herb grows beſt when moſt trodden down: Theſe Veſſels are brighteſt, when moſt ſcoured: There is great need God's Children ſhould be in Heavineſs, to poiſe their ſpirits, and prevent Wantonneſs. The Vine muſt be lopt, or it will grow wild: Corn-bearing Fields muſt be broken up: Afflictions never do the Church hurt; but Proſperity often rots it, and rocks it aſleep, to its great Prejudice, if not its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Subverſion: Miniſters uſually ſtand in the Front, and are put upon the hotteſt Service; the Fire is continually burning on the Brazen Altar: The Prieſts of old muſt firſt enter <hi>Jordan,</hi> and be the laſt ſtanding <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3. 8,—17.</note> in the midſt thereof: Satan's Malice is moſt at them, and God uſually furniſheth them with more Magnanimity than others. He that ſtill governs the World with Infinite Wiſdom, hath appointed to the ſons of men their peculiar Office, Station, and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world, and qualifies them with Gifts proportionably; manageth their Work for them, proſpereth their Undertakings, accepteth their faithful Service, and will give them abundant Recompence: Yea, their Work is their Wages; it comes with Meat in its Mouth. A Gracious Heaven
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:103239:5"/> is the Preludium of a Glorious Heaven; yea, there's much of Glory upon a ſuffering Miniſter or Chriſtian: When they are load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Dirt and Obloquy, even then the Spirit of Glory and of God reſteth on them. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 16.</note> It's no diminution, but a manifeſtation of God's Glory, when it ſhines through the Glaſs of Creatures; yea, the leſs of the Creatures Worth is diſcovered, the more of God is illuſtrated. We have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7.</note> the Power may be of God, and not of us. King <hi>Solomon</hi> muſt have a Thouſand, if Vine-dreſſers and Fruit-keepers have their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Song</hi> 8. 12.</note> Two hundred. Let Miniſters be inviſible, ſo Chriſt be Illuſtrious: As Precious Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> ſaid, <hi>So God's Work be done, I am content to be withdrawn out of ſight.</hi> So ſome interpret that Text, <hi>John</hi> 3. 29. as though the Friend of the Bridegrrom will not be ſeen in the Treaty, but he ſtands behind the Curtain, and hears the Bridegroom's Voice, and the Bride's Conſent, and greatly rejoiceth, becauſe the Match is likely to go on: But the more Nothing a Miniſter is in his own eyes, the more doth God magnify him: As the Wife ſhines in the Beams of her Husband's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Riches, ſo alſo doth God in ſome
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:103239:6"/> ſenſe ſhine in his Servants Gifts and Graces. Our Thoughts muſt go beyond the Gift, to the Giver. A clear tranſparent Glaſs ſet in the Sun, renders the Sun moſt illuſtrious, the Chryſtal is ſcarce viſible, the Sun is all; yet to our eyes the radiant Sun-beams are more beautiful by the Reflection through the Glaſs, than ſhining directly upon us; but the Glaſs gives not ſplendor to the Sun, but receives all from it; thus is Chriſt all in all: And as theſe Glaſſes are quickly broken, and rendred uſeleſs, ſo are Miniſters, but the Sun remains in its motion, and ſhines ſtill; for the Sun depends not on the Glaſs, but the Glaſs on the Sun; yea, God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thinks fit to break the Glaſs we are admiring, that our eyes may be intent upon the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and behold all Beauties in him, who is the Lord our Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. God in Wiſdom hath thought fit to cauſe an Eclypſe in the Firmament of his Church in theſe Nations, by hiding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lights under a Buſhel, about Thirty Years; and alſo tranſlated moſt of them into an Upper Region, where they ſhine brighteſt in their proper Orb, tho to us they diſappear: The breaking of the Shell is the brightning of the Pearl; they were never ſo bright below as they are now above; once
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:103239:6"/> they ſaw <hi>through a glaſs darkly, now</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>face to face;</hi> and laying aſide this Glaſs, <hi>with open face immediately they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image, from glory to glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Bleſſed Souls, now with God, are ſubject neither to the black Miſts of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ignorance, nor to foggy Vapours of Sinful Defects, nor do they feel or fear the beſpattering Dirt of Opprobrious Scorns, of black-mouth'd Slanderers, but are receiv'd up into Heaven by this Cloud of Death, that hath hid them out of our ſight, and hindred our Converſe with them; yet they have dropt the Mantle of good Examples, which ſtill we have; and obſervant Eyes, and diligent Pens have drawn ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Patriots in lively Colours, in which we may behold much of God's Image in the face of their converſings amongſt men, and Converſations both in their Perſonal and Publick Capacities: This is a petty Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; and much good ſervice is done to ſucceeding Ages hereby; by which they <hi>being dead, yet ſpeak;</hi> yea, ſpiritual life is transfuſed to Readers, through the Lines and Leaves tranſmitted to them: Bleſſed be God for theſe famous Heroes: If the <hi>Jews</hi> mentioned ſuch Brave Men dead, with
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:103239:7"/> Notes of Remark, [as <hi>Rabbi Hillel</hi> of Bleſſed Memory], Why ſhould not <hi>the memory of the juſt be bleſſed?</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 7.</note> there's a vaſt difference in the ears of Proteſtants, betwixt Bleſſed <hi>Bradford</hi> and Bloody <hi>Bonner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men uſually ſay, when they have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Corps of their dead Relations, and left them in the Duſt, that they have done their laſt Office to them, or for them: But I judge that to be a groſs miſtake, for there are ſeveral Offices to which we are bound on their behalf. 1. We ought to lament their Death as a ſad loſs for the Church of God, (I ſpeak of pious and uſeful Perſons) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 10.</note> decent Funeral Solemnities were kept a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time in Scripture. 2. Obſerving and complying with the Commands and the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. 10.</note> Counſels of the Dead, ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren. 3. Giving the Dead deſerved Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 4. Vindication of their Reputation according to truth. 5. Monuments erected for a Memorial, as <hi>Jacob</hi> over <hi>Rachel</hi>'s <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. 20. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 17. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 34.</note> Grave. 6. Funeral Elegies, as <hi>David</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan.</hi> 7. Owning our Father's God and Covenant; ſo <hi>Solomon.</hi> 8. Manifeſting Demonſtrations of dead Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Charity and Piety, as the Widows for <hi>Dorcas.</hi> 9. An exact imitation of their
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:103239:7"/> praiſe-worthy Acts. 10. Communion with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22.</note> dead Saints, believing that there are ſuch rejoycing in their Glory, hoping in a ſhort time to be with them, thinking of them, ſtudying Conformity to them, that we may do God's Will on Earth, as it's done in Heaven. 11. Yea, ſomething is alſo due from us to the ſurviving Relations of our pious dead Friends, as <hi>David</hi> ſhewed kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 2.</note> to <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s ſeed. All this (and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly more) without the imputation of Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, may ſurviving Chriſtians do, when their gracious Friends and Relations diſappear in this Lower World; only let us not admire them, but God in them; ſo ſaith the Text, 2 Theſ. 1. 10. <hi>When he ſhall come to be glorified in his ſaints, and to be admired in all them that believe.</hi> Mark it, Gods holieſt Saints must not be admired, but God in them: Our Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion must not reſpect Men ſimply, but be terminated upon God through them: Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-worſhip is very natural to us, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we ſee more than ordinary excellency in the Creature, or receive ſome ſingular Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereby. The great Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> was twice guilty of Angel-adoration, and was twice admoniſhed againſt it. But doubtleſs it is a good Work, and no deſpicable Office of
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:103239:8"/> ſurviving Friends to commemorate the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Acts of dead Miniſters or Chriſtians of conſiderable Magnitude and Figure in the Church.</p>
            <p>This is my Apology for writing this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, knowing how acceptable it will be to Chriſtian Friends, Natural Relations, and to the Church of God; indeed he was ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all, and very imitable in the Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his Life, and Circumſtances that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to his Death; what was praiſe-worthy in him, let God have the Glory of it; what is defective in the Copy or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber, let Charity draw a Curtain over both.</p>
            <p>I do find that the Servants of God have been very careful and critical in Writing the Lives of Eminent Men, as <hi>Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> wrote the Life of <hi>Luther, Junius</hi> of <hi>Urſin, Beza</hi> of <hi>Calvin, Antonius Jaius</hi> of <hi>Beza, Joſias Simlerus</hi> of <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> Dr. <hi>Humphry</hi> of Bp. <hi>Jewell,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Melchior Adamus</hi> hath ſummed them up together, and Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark</hi> hath made many Collections; neither the Perſon deſcribed, nor the Scribe anſwering theſe men of God, it doth make me bluſh to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this Undertaking, eſpecially in this ſo Critical Age; but this I dare ſay, The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:103239:8"/> or Perſon treated of, was full of good Works, and he that treats thereon is full of Good-Will.</p>
            <p>Nor have I related all that might have been writ, and that he himſelf writ, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it not convenient, becauſe it might be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive: Take this in good part, live up to it, pray for the weak Tranſcriber, and beg hard that God would raiſe up many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to make up this and other Vacancies made of late by the Death of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Miniſters, which ſeems to be a ſad Omen and dreadful Prognoſtick of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolating Judgment approaching; for our Defence is departing from us; the Chariots and Horſemen of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are aſcending in a Fiery Chariot; Stakes are taken out of the Hedge, that Wild Beaſts may enter; Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are removed; the Houſe totters; we have loſt much good Blood; <hi>Jacob's</hi> Face looks pale: May our dear Lord once at laſt reſtore his Miniſters to their Publick Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, pour out a Spirit of Prayer, cauſe an univerſal caſting of melted Sinners into the Mould of the Goſpel, and revive a Work of Reformation, that the promiſe may be performed in Iſaiah 29. 22, 23. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, who redeemed Abraham, concerning the houſe of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob:</hi>
               <pb n="x" facs="tcp:103239:9"/> 
               <hi>Jacob ſhall not now be aſhamed, neither ſhall his face now wax pale. But when he ſeeth his children, the work of mine hands in the midſt of him they ſhall ſanctify my name, and ſanctify the holy one of Jacob, and ſhall fear the God of Iſrael.</hi> Amen. So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 29. 1694.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103239:9"/>
            <head>A SHORT Hiſtorical Account OF THE LIFE and DEATH OF Mr. <hi>Nathanael Heywood,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Nathanael Heywood</hi> was Born in <hi>Little Leaver</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton le-Moors</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> deſcended of godly and uſeful Parents <hi>(Richard</hi> and <hi>Alice Heywood);</hi> he was baptized in the Pariſh-Church, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 16. 1633. During his Infancy he was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weak and ſickly, much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103239:10"/> with Fits of Convulſion, and was frequently under the ſentence of Death, in the apprehenſion of all Spectators: His tender-hearted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents often gave him up for gone; but God, who quickneth the dead, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him from the gates of the grave, that by him he might raiſe ſinners from Damnable Death to Spiritual Life. Notwithſtanding thoſe violent Fits did ſo weaken his Spirits, that in his younger days he was not judged fit to be trained up for the Miniſtry; and therefore his Parents did frequently take him from School, and ſet him to learn to Write and caſt Accompts, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſending him to <hi>London</hi> for an Apprentice. But he recruiting as to natural ſtrength, and they being encouraged by his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary capacity for Learning, kept him ſtill at School, having the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of a learned and diligent Maſter near at hand, who encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged them much to breed him a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103239:10"/> Scholar; eſpecially obſerving his inclinations that way: At laſt they reſolved upon it; and when he had paſſed thoſe juvenile Studies, at School, making good proficiency (notwithſtanding his frequent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions), he was judged ready for the Univerſity at fourteen years of Age; whither he went, and was admitted, <hi>May</hi> 4. 1648. in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> he was well approved of for School-learning, and fell cloſe to his ſtudies, performed the uſual Exerciſes with applauſe: He was of pregnant Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parts, of a quick Apprehenſion, ſolid Judgment, tenacious Memory; which ſeldom meet in one Perſon; he was fit to manage what he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook with great agility and faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: So that he profited in Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical learning beyond his equals.</p>
            <p>As for Religion, as yet his heart was not ſeaſoned with a Principle of Saving Grace; though he was Religiouſly Educated, complying
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103239:11"/> with holy Exerciſes, loved God's People, and was not tainted with groſs ſcandals; yet he had not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Evil of Sin, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of Nature, the Neceſſity of Chriſt, till he was providentially brought under the Miniſtry of Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Fellow of <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> Colledge, Preacher at St. <hi>Gyles</hi>'s by whoſe plain and powerful preaching, his heart was ſmitten with a ſound Conviction, which coſt him many ſad thoughts of heart, as well as tears, but ended at laſt in a ſound Converſion, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Covenanting with God, and centring his Soul by Faith on Jeſus Chriſt. Then he aſſociated with ſerious Chriſtians, and walked ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily; howbeit, he complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his backſlidings, which he repented of, and his Soul was heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. When he had taken his Degree, he went to <hi>London,</hi> and there heard Mr. <hi>Peter Sterry;</hi> and was much taken with his Parts, and manner of preaching.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103239:11"/>
            <p>When he came down into the Countrey, his Father judged it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to diſpoſe of him under the Tuition of ſome Reverend Miniſter, by whoſe care and example he might be prepared for further ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And it pleaſed God in his providence to fix him in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that ſolid judicious Divine, Mr. <hi>Edward Gee,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton;</hi> where he continued about two years, ſtudying hard, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelf orderly, and profited much: So that he often bleſſed God for the good he met with in that family. And indeed he was mould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and modelled into the method, manners, and practices of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Eminent man of God; whoſe excellent treatiſes of Prayer and Government, ſpeak his real worth: A man of great Learning, Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxneſs, and exact Holineſs; a moſt ſubſtantial Scriptural Preacher, Son to that famous Mr. <hi>Gee,</hi> mentioned by Hiſtorians in the fall at <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friars.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:103239:12"/>
            <p>Whilſt Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> lived in Mr. <hi>Gee</hi>'s Family, God directed his thoughts to a young Gentlewoman in the neighbourhood, Mrs. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Parre,</hi> near to Dr. <hi>Parre,</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Iſle of Man;</hi> whom in convenient time he Married, and ſhe became a pious, prudent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Wife to him; by whom he had ſeveral Children, Six whereof are yet living, Two Sons, and Four Daughters; his elder Son ſucceeds in his Father's place, as Paſtour to that people, in their new-erected Meeting-place; a young man of pregnant Parts, and exemplary Piety.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was Married, it pleaſed God to give him a Call to a people in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> for he had a great deſire to be employed in his Lord's work; and that very day that an Invitation came to him, he told the Meſſenger he had been ſpending moſt of it in Faſting and Prayer; wherein he found his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103239:12"/> heart much enlarged, and looked upon that Call as an Anſwer of Prayer; and thereupon freely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced it, and in convenient ſeaſon took a journey.</p>
            <p>The place to which he was called was <hi>Illingworth</hi> Chappel, in the Viccaridge of <hi>Halifax</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire.</hi> When he had preached a day or two with them, the people laid hold of him, and engaged him to ſettle with them, which he did; and continued three or four years, and was an inſtrument of much good in that place, having a full Auditory, and ſome ſeals of his Miniſtry. But the Devil envying the ſucceſs of the Goſpel, raiſed up ſome potent Adverſaries againſt him, who maligned and oppoſed him for his faithfulneſs in plain ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions. Some meetings there was about his continuance; one ſaid to him, Mr. <hi>Heywood,</hi> You have raiſed differences and diſturbances ſince you came: He anſwered, I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103239:13"/> have not ſought the peace of the place, but the good of it. Which he ruminated upon, and could not tell what to make of that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not remembring, that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal deſign of the Goſpel, and its Publiſhers, is the good of Souls; but the accidental fruit of it, is diſſention, through the corruption of mens hearts, according to what our Bleſſed Lord expreſſed, <hi>Think</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>not that I am come to ſend peace on earth: I came not to ſend peace, but a ſword.</hi> In this controverſie about his ſtay, or removal, an earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was ſent to him by the people of <hi>Orms-Church,</hi> to come to them; he hearkened to them, having ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral diſcouragements at <hi>Illing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> not here fit to be named; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome cordial Friends in that Congregation ſtuck cloſe to him, and challenged an intereſt in him; both ſides uſing more than ordinary arguments and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, did exceedingly puzzle him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103239:13"/> and ſet him upon the rack of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence: He earneſtly ſought to God about it, he begged the advice and prayers of Friends, and at laſt was counſelled to refer the buſineſs to ſeveral Miniſters indifferently cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by both ſides, to hear what could be ſaid, underſtand circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and give their judgments in this weighty caſe, to which of theſe places his way was moſt clear; indeed a third put in vigorouſly for him, <hi>viz. Thornton</hi> in <hi>Bradford</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; but the controverſie was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwixt thoſe two, <hi>Ormskirk</hi> and <hi>Illingworth;</hi> Miniſters met about this concern at <hi>Wigan</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> in <hi>January</hi> 1656. and two or three of the Inhabitants of thoſe three forementioned places; much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate there was, and ſome hard words paſſed; the buſineſs was dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficult, and coſt many hours di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, both in the day and in the evening; and upon a ſerious view of the reaſons on all hands, at laſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103239:14"/> the Miniſters concluded that his way was clear to leave <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> and betake himſelf to <hi>Ormskirk</hi> which being a great Pariſh, and a conſiderable Market-Town, and the people vacant, and very impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, they judged that he might do God and his Church more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in that great place: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his own inclinations carried him moſt that way, upon ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar reaſons: He removed with his Family thither in the Spring, 1657. where he was entertained with much reſpect, and great ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: And there he laboured faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently in the courſe of his publick Miniſtry, private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, viſiting the Sick, till <hi>Auguſt</hi> 24, 1662. that black Dooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, wherein ſo many were ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and ſtruck dead in Law as to any publick Service.</p>
            <p>The Annual Incomes of this Vicaridge were very ſmall, not amounting to above 30 <hi>l.</hi> a year;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103239:14"/> yet there was an Augmentation added of 50 <hi>l.</hi> a year by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> upon an Itinerant Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, which had been long fixed upon the Miniſter of that place. There were four of them in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> this was one; and 200 <hi>l. per An.</hi> was paid out of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to thoſe four; this was paid by ſeveral Truſtees at the Audit.</p>
            <p>At the return of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. one Mr. <hi>Stanninghaugh,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Augham,</hi> worth 140 <hi>l.</hi> a year, about two Miles from <hi>Ormskirk,</hi> rode up to <hi>London,</hi> and by the help of Friends ſurreptitiouſly obtained this 50 <hi>l.</hi> a year to be ſetled upon himſelf; which gave occaſion to ſome perſons to reflect upon a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> preached at <hi>Ormſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> upon a day of Thankſgiving for the King's Reſtoration, upon 2 Sam. 19. 30. <hi>And</hi> Mephiboſheth <hi>ſaid unto the king, Yea, let him take all, foraſmuch as my lord the king is come again in peace unto his own</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103239:15"/> 
               <hi>houſe.</hi> Which was indeed an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent Diſcourſe, greatly approved and highly applauded by all, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially the Gentry, who earneſtly ſollicited him to print it, but he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſed; not out of diſloyalty, but modeſty; not becauſe he durſt not own his Sovereign, but he was not willing to be much taken notice of in the world.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> digeſted this diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous carriage of his Neighbour and pretended Friend, with great aequanimity and calmneſs; and it proved a Worm to the one, and at Bleſſing to the other: for though this Mr. <hi>Stanninghaugh</hi>'s Parſonage was 148 <hi>l.</hi> a year, and his Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was 30 <hi>l.</hi> a year, and this 50 <hi>l.</hi> yearly, and he had no Child, yet he left nothing at his death but Debt, and his Wife in a poor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>But it pleaſed God from that time to bleſs Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi>'s ſmall Incomes incredibly; and 'tis next
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103239:15"/> to a Miracle to conſider what great things he did, when ſhortly after he was turn'd out of all, he paid ſome Debts, and maintained his numerous Family in a good <hi>deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> for he had nine Children, whereof ſix are yet living; took a Leaſe for Three Lives of, an Houſe and Land, paid 60 <hi>l.</hi> built a good part of it; paid 30 <hi>l.</hi> for buying but a Leaſe elſewhere; maintained his two Sons at School at <hi>Holland,</hi> which coſt him 14 <hi>l.</hi> a year; ſent one to Mr. <hi>Frankland,</hi> to be educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Univerſity-learning; beſides many ſore Sickneſſes in his Family. Yet ſuch was the bleſſing of God, that he waded through all, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contracting any Debt, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increaſing his Eſtate out of his ſmall Incomes: This Holy Man was very ſenſible of this ſtrange Providence, and often expreſſed it with admiring thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>In the year 1662, <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. that fatal day ſtruck him civilly dead
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103239:16"/> with the reſt of his Brethren; how beit he continu'd his publick Preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in the Church after that day without diſturbance, till the place was filled up with a new Vicar, on Mr. <hi>Aſhworth</hi> a Schoolmaſter, who lived ſix or eight Miles from thence taught his School, rode thither or <hi>Saturday,</hi> and back on <hi>Monday</hi> morn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing; was abſent all the week for ſeveral years: ſo that Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> ſtill ſeemed to have the ſole charge of that Town and Pariſh, viſiting the Sick, inſtructing them, praying with them, preaching privately to them as occaſion was offered. He was abundant in the work of the Lord, not only in his own Pariſh, but at <hi>Wigan, Warrington, Lever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pool, Preſton, Eccleſton,</hi> and upon a call in more remote places.</p>
            <p>But in his own Pariſh, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his old Hearers, he was in Labours more abundant; he uſually preach'd twice on a Lords day, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeveral times in Week-days, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103239:16"/> his Labours in ſeveral parts of the Pariſh, both in the day and night: Yea, in times of great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he hath preach'd at one houſe the beginning of the night, and then gone two Miles a-foot over Moſſes, and preach'd toward morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to another Company at another houſe.</p>
            <p>Nor was he ſcant and ſhort in his Sermons, but uſually very long, two hours at leaſt, often three; yea, ſometimes he would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued four or five hours praying and preaching, his heart was ſo fully ſet upon his Maſter's work, that he forgot his own ſtrength, and his Hearers patience. Nor did he tediouſly dream over his work, but was full of zeal, vigour, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and affection, often ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his voice beyond what his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtrength could well bear, which occaſioned torturing and mortal Diſeaſes; like a Candle, he ſpent himſelf to give others light.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103239:17"/>
            <p>Neither was he <hi>[vox &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terea nihil]</hi> a meer voice, and no more; like ſome Preachers, that like Thunder give a loud crack without a diſtinct ſound or ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cancy; no, his Sermons were ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fed with ſolid Divinity, Scripture Arguments, alluring Similies, heart melting Paſſages. He was an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent Text man, producing ſolid Interpretations. An experienc'd Caſuiſt, reſolving Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience with great ſatisfaction. A clear Diſputant, ſtating Contro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſies ſolidly and ſubſtantially anſwering Objections learnedly and diſtinctly, and proving the Truth demonſtratively. He was a pathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tical Preacher, driving the Nail home, in cloſe Convictions of Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, warm Exhortations to Converſion, or to particular Du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, plain and undeniable Directi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, ſtill laying open, and obvia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting Satan's wiles, the deceits of a bad heart, and inſnaring inſinua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103239:17"/> of a wicked world; rifling the Conſcience by a thorough Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination; comforting God's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with ſweet Goſpel-Promiſes.</p>
            <p>This, this indeed was his Maſter-piece, and main Scope in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to lay open the Beauties and Excellencies of the Bleſſed Jeſus, and Sinners great neceſſity of him; diſplaying in lively colours the love of God in ſending his Son, the love of Chriſt in the unparallel'd work of Redemption; the Offices, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes and Undertakings of the Son of God; unfolding the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, the Operations of the Spirit; in applying the Merits of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The truth of this appears in two excellent Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, printed ſince his Death, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed out of his own Notes, as he preached them the ſame year he died: The one called <hi>[Chriſt the Beſt Gift]</hi> which was grounded on <hi>John</hi> 4. 10. The other entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>[Chriſt the Beſt Maſter]</hi> ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103239:18"/> upon <hi>John</hi> 13. 13. Two exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent Treatiſes, Bound up together Printed after his death; for he would never be perſuaded to pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh any thing; though, doubtleſs they would have been more Acu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, if he had imagined they ſhould have ſeen the light: But ſuch as they are, they have proved very acceptable and profitable to the Church of God: Many have read them with pleaſure; and ſome good Divines have quoted paſſages out of them.</p>
            <p>His labours in the Miniſtry were ſo exceedingly welcome, that the loſs of him in publick work was greatly bewailed by the whole Town and Pariſh; he was beloved of all, good and bad. A poor ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norant man came to him when he was turned out, ſaying, Ah! Mr <hi>Heywood,</hi> we would gladly have you Preach again in the Church. Yes, ſaid he, I would as gladly Preach as you deſire it, if I could
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103239:18"/> do it with a ſafe Conſcience in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming: The man replied, Oh Sir! many a man now-a-days makes a great gaſh in his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, cannot you make a little nick in yours?</p>
            <p>That was a remarkable paſſage which fell out at <hi>Ormskirk,</hi> on <hi>July</hi> 30, 1662. which Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> thus deſcribes in a Letter to a Friend; About four a Clock that day in the Afternoon, was a dreadful Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning for a long time together; and in the Town of <hi>Ormskirk,</hi> and about it, fell a great ſhower of Hail in a terrible Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; Hailſtones were as big as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Apples, ſome ſay Nine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches compaſs; one Stone that I took up was above Four Inches, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had thawed in my hand; the Hail broke all our Glaſs Windows Weſtward, we have not one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril whole on our backſide; ſo it is with moſt of the houſes in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Town; it hath cut off all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103239:19"/> the Ears of our ſtanding Corn, ſo that moſt Fields that were full of excellent Barley, and other Grain, are not worth Reaping: It hath ſhaken the Apple-trees, and in ſome places bruiſed the Apples in pieces; the Hail cut Boughs from Trees; and ſome ſay there are ſtrange Apparitions in the Air (of which I ſhall give you a further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.) All, eſpecially the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, were much terrified, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it had been the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; certainly it was a ſad ſign and effect of God's heavy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with us; and I wiſh it be not a preſage of more abiding Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. They tell me, that my ſmall ſhare of loſs will amount to 10 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt; in half an hour all this hurt was done. The Lord ſanctify this ſudden ſtroke to me and my poor people. Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> in his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hath this Story, and mentions Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> his atteſtation of it, which yet I thought fit to relate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103239:19"/> here; partly becauſe this is fuller than he relates it; partly to ſhew how obſervant this holy man was of the remarkable Providences of God. It was his obſervation, That this natural ſtorm was a ſad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a moral ſtorm on Miniſters and Churches, which fell the very month after, that rooted up ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſeful fruit-bearing trees, marred ſo much good fruit, and ſhattered the glaſs by which the light of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-truth is conveyed into the houſe of God. This good man was ſo endeared to this People, that he was reſolved never to part from them till death made the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce; of whom thus he writes: I have a loving, though poor, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, though ignorant People; they flock in very great numbers to the Ordinances, and I have hopes of doing ſome good (it may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun) amongſt them: I had ſome motion to Conform, but I will not change upon any account
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103239:20"/> whatſoever; let me have your prayers, help me for this poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which I love as my own Child, and long after in the bowels of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>He had frequent diſtempers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his body, which much promoted God's work upon his heart: In the year 1667. he had a violent diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which in a fortnights time brought his body very low; and by that time he was recovered, his dear Wife fell into a ſad languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſeaſe, which threatned death; beſides grievous afflictions in her Spirit, and ſad apprehenſions of death for above a month together; a Swelling in her Throat, which increaſed to a hard Tumour in the hollow of her Throat, which ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably, in the eye of Reaſon, threatned Death; but beyond all expectation, God did graciouſly remove that, and raiſed her up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in mercy to the Family. In the year 1670. his Son <hi>Nathanael</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:103239:20"/> was ſtrangely taken with Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Fits, which tortured and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted his Face, Limbs, every part of his Body in a prodigious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but God alſo at laſt raiſed him up upon the Prayers of his People. But theſe Providences found him work for, and quickned his Spirit in Prayer.</p>
            <p>In <hi>October</hi> 1671. Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> fell into a malignant Feaver, which (as his two Doctors, Dr. <hi>Fife,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Grundy</hi> ſaid) had ſeized the Nerves, and Spirits, and Brain; he was not in extremity of pain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as the Phyſitians ſaid) the diſeaſe lay not ſo much in the Blood: Upon the 13th. day, after he begun, he was judged to be a gone man; Dr. <hi>Fife</hi> (a boyſterous man, and Juſtice of the Peace, in the <hi>Fild-countrey</hi> near <hi>Garſtand)</hi> called for a Candle, and bade him open his mouth, which when he had looked into, he ſwore a great Oath, and ſaid, his Tongue is as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103239:21"/> black as a Thraſh; call the Miſtreſs of the houſe, ſaid he, let him ſet all things in order, and make his Will for he's a gone man; theſe words aſtoniſhed his Family; but his own and only ſurviving Siſter, being preſent, and hearing theſe confident Expreſſions, gathered encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thought within herſelf, This is but a man, and may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; God is God, and can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute him. Thus Dr. <hi>Fife</hi> left him as hopeleſs, and ſaid, it was in vain to give him any thing: But before he came to his own houſe, at <hi>Hough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Tower,</hi> a Feaver ſeized violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Doctor himſelf, and in a few days made an end of him; ſo he never returned home alive But from that very day Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> began to amend, the Feaver abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is likely that was a Criſis, when the diſeaſe was at its height; for it was a dreadful day and night, he had all the ſymptoms of death upon him; but God had mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103239:21"/> him, as upon ſick <hi>Epaphroditus;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 27.</note> God had much work for him to do: But he continued under weakneſs and ſome diſorder in his Head; for he could not be perſuaded that he was at home, confidently affirming he was at <hi>Bickerſtaff,</hi> where indeed he was immediately before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun his diſtemper, to viſit Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Stanly,</hi> who was begun in a Feaver, and died ſhortly after; Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> would needs be helped to the Window to ſee the Funeral paſs by to the Church.</p>
            <p>This ſore ſickneſs was in the year 1671. and the King's Licenſes came out in the year following 1672. and indeed hitherto he had very little or no diſturbance in his preaching-work, God was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him both for ſervice and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This ſickneſs preceded ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; God laid the foundation low, deſigning to build high; and often God thinks fit to lay the faireſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours upon a ſable bottom; ſo God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103239:22"/> paſſed the ſentence of death upon him immediately before this petty reſurrection; for in the Spring fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing came out the Liberty to Preach; Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> cordially embraced it, and had two Chappels Licenſed, <hi>viz. Bickerſtaff,</hi> adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Lady <hi>Stanly</hi>'s houſe, two Miles South from <hi>Ormskirk;</hi> the other was <hi>Scaresbrick,</hi> two Miles North from the Pariſh-Church, both in <hi>Ormskirk</hi> Pariſh; theſe he ſupplied conſtantly, preaching at the one Chappel one day, at the other the next Lord's day; of which he thus writes: I bleſs God my Congregation is numerous and attentive; Oh! that they were as fruitful! my Family is healthful, Oh! that they were more holy!</p>
            <p>He continued two years in theſe two Chappels; but about <hi>April</hi> 9, 1674. he thus writes: I have had more trouble and oppoſition in my Miniſterial employment theſe four Months laſt paſt, than ever I had
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103239:22"/> in all my life, yet am not taken off to this day; Archers have ſorely griev'd us and ſhot at us 34 Arrows (I mean Warrants) but our Bow abides in ſtrength, by the hands of the Mighty God of <hi>Jacob;</hi> Officers have come Eighteen Lord's days together, but have not as yet ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered us,—how eaſy is it for God to ſave us while we ſerve him, if we could believe? I am encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to hope that ſome good is done, or may be done, by my poor labours in this ſeaſon, and 'tis no ill ſign when Satan rageth ſo violently againſt us: God can work without, or againſt means, and can work by improbable means to accompliſh great ends. I was never more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly born up under ſtorms, nor ſtrengthened againſt difficulties in all my life; it may be my time is but ſhort, and my work near an end; Oh! that I may live and die in God's work and way, and be faithful unto death! Dear Brother,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103239:23"/> let my condition have a deeper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on your heart than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Two Warrants (one for 20 <hi>l.</hi> the other for 40 <hi>l.)</hi> have been out againſt me theſe Seven Weeks, but we keep our doors faſt Barred, and the Officers are very Civil to us,—Oh! that I could ſee you! I have no Horſe, but go all my Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys on foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> 13, 1674. He thus writes: I bleſs God my Liberty (notwithſtanding all my troubles) is not wholly loſt, but ſometimes diſturbed; we meet in fear, yet we meet in both Chappels: No Warrant is ſent for a Month or more, and my Auditory increaſeth again; Oh! that I had an heart to improve late experiences and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent opportunities, and do my duty, leaving the iſſue to him that judgeth righteouſly!</p>
            <p>But his exceſſive Pains (though refreſhing to his Spirit) yet were waſting to his Body; for about
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103239:23"/> that time thus he writes: I am ſtill at work in both Chappels,—but I am much caſt down with pains and weakneſs of Body, having overgone my ſtrength, and waſted my ſelf in theſe intervals of Liberty God hath given us: But I have no reaſon to repent any thing I could ever do for ſo good a Maſter; Oh! that I had done more, and better!</p>
            <p>About the ſame time he Writes thus: Some aſſaults Satan hath made upon me with a right-hand Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; the whole Pariſh of <hi>Aughton</hi> have been importunate with me, to put my ſelf into a capacity for their Parſonage (worth Seven or Eightſcore Pond <hi>per Annum);</hi> the Biſhop <hi>(i. e.</hi> Dr. <hi>Wilkins)</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth favour to me in it; but God did not leave me ſo much as to have any ſerious thoughts to yeild to that Temptation,—I do preach ſtill, but not ſo conſtantly, nor in ſo full a Congregration as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103239:24"/> formerly. Dear Brother, I beſeech you for the Lord's ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, ſtrive together with me, in your Prayers to God for me, you know for what, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt after many ſtruglings, threatnings, affrightings, peoples withdrawings and rallying again, a ſtratagem was contrived to knock all dead at a blow; ſome Deputy-Lieutenants ſent ſome Soldiers to take Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> in the Pulpit; and though it was known, yet they met in <hi>Bickerſtaff</hi> Chappel; Lady <hi>Stanly</hi> came out of her Gallery, and placed herſelf near the Pulpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, hoping to over-aw their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and obſtruct their deſigns; the Soldiers ſtood without, while Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was at prayer; but when he had prayed, they ruſhed in, and required him to come down, and go along with them; he mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired the favour of them, that they would give him leave to preach, and he would go along
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103239:24"/> with them; but they rudely run towards the Pulpit; the Lady would have ſtopp'd them, but they preſſed forward, opened the Pulpit door, got hold of his Coat and tore it, and in a ſort pull'd him out, and took him away with them ſtraight to <hi>Holland;</hi> nor could the Lady's mediation prevail to procure him a little refreſhment; only in the road he grew ſaint, and deſired them to call with him at an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, which they did, and the Landlady (though he had no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with her) was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kind to him, and ſaid, he ſhould have any thing ſhe had in the houſe; but thoſe Rogues, ſaid ſhe, ſhall not have a morſel that took him; ſo they carried him away to an Alehouſe in <hi>Holland,</hi> where he lodged that night; and from whence thus writ to his Wife:</p>
            <p>—I am very well, I bleſs God, and never in greater honour,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103239:25"/> or ſo highly advanced in all my life; I was pulled out of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit with a Piſtol lifted up at my head, and a God-dam-me in mine ears, but the man repents his raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and wiſhes he had let me preach, for he never heard a better prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But be not troubled, God hath ſhewed me more mercy than I can be thankful for: Oh! help me to praiſe him! Oh! what cauſe have we to rejoice in ſuffering upon this account! God will have Glory, and his Church the benefit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I fear it muſt be an Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or promiſe not to preach, which is my very life,—</p>
            <p>But God in his gracious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence did alſo ſcatter this cloud; for the day after, when it was noiſed abroad that Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was taken, abundance of People, and many conſiderable Gentlemen, and ſome that were no friends to his Cauſe, yet out of reſpect to his Perſon, mediated for him; yea, ſeveral of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103239:25"/> good report, and intimate with the Juſtices, offered to be Bound for his appearance, and to give any ſecurity that ſhould be required. The Juſtices then tendred him the <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath; he was in a ſtrait, for if he peremptorily refuſed it, they had ſome advantage againſt him; he told them that perſons muſt ſwear in judgment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſired ſome time to conſider of it, which was conſented to: And ſeeing ſuch an appearance of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all ranks for him, they gave him reſpite; and liberty to go home till the next Quarter-Seſſions, which was to be at <hi>Wigan</hi> a Month after; but they bound him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Seſſions.</p>
            <p>Thus he was delivered out of that ſnare, and went home, and writ a Letter that day, dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 28. 1674.—Pray help me to praiſe God, and remember a poor ſufferer for the Goſpel in your prayers: People do ſo throng in to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:103239:26"/> ſee me, now I am come home again, that I have not time to write fully to you, but commit you to God and his protection, that you may long enjoy, and fruitfully improve that ſweet Liberty in God's Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, which, I doubt, I have loſt; and indeed ſo it proved.</p>
            <p>The Seſſions at <hi>Wigan</hi> came on, he attended there according to his Bonds; ſeveral Juſtices appeared for him, and his friends came to ſee the iſſue, and to mediate for him: Old Lady <hi>Stanly</hi> came herſelf, and her Husband, Mr. <hi>Henry Hoghton</hi> (a Juſtice of Peace); yea, Mr. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Baniſter</hi> of <hi>Bank,</hi> and ſeveral others, ſpoke much on his behalf; another Juſtice then upon the Bench ſaid, If Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was ſent to <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Goal, he ſhould be as comfortably maintained, and as honourably releaſed as ever any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner was; ſome of his Adverſaries ſeeing which way the Court incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſlunk away in a diſcontent,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103239:26"/> took Horſe and rid home; ſo the ſnare was again broken, and Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was diſmiſſed to the joy of his Friends, vexation of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and amazement of all that heard of it.</p>
            <p>Other ſnares were laid to entrap him upon the Five-Mile Act, but no body could be brought to ſwear that he lived in the Town, though Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> was uſually at home, and converſed openly in the Town, he was ſo generally beloved. A Warrant was iſſued out to diſtrain upon Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi>'s goods for 20 <hi>l.</hi> but the Officers ſaid the doors were ſhut, and they had no orders to break them; yet they might have taken advantage if they had been ſevere, but indeed they were generally very favourable: It's true, the doors were kept faſt for half a year toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till things wore off, and they never got a pennyworth of his goods, which was looked upon as a wonderful ſtrange Providence;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103239:27"/> for Children and others were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently paſſing and repaſſing through the out-doors, foreſide and backſide. God took him off his work by mens rigour, and obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted his former diligence by his own immediate hand upon his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, much what at the ſame time; and thus he writes,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 7. 1675.—I am glad your precious Liberty is continued; I have nothing to do now at home, but am much abroad, which is an heavy burthen to me; pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, increaſe your fervent prayers for me; Riding is very painful to me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1675/6. he writes thus: I am now very buſie, bleſſed be God, and theſe holy days (ſo called) when others play, I work, having preach'd oftener hereabouts in a few days, than I did in the whole year; I was lately at <hi>Cheſter</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compelled thither by the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of friends) where I preached
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103239:27"/> thrice, and had great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; God hath much people (I believe) in that place; they would perſuade me to live with them, but I am reſolved to ſtick here yet, where Providence hath ſo eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetled me, preſerved, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for me,—My Lads ſeem to be inclin'd to the Miniſtry.—Who knows but God may be fitting Inſtruments for his work in the next Age! for my part I can ſee no reaſon to look for any thing but Judgments in this.</p>
            <p>He was always a zealous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugner of, and a notable Champion againſt Papiſts, of whom there be great ſtore in thoſe parts. When Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> hath been ſent for to viſit ſick Perſons, (in which work he was conſtant, careful, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſucceſsful) Popiſh Friends, or Neighbours would often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſome Popiſh Prieſt, or one of their Religion, to come alſo to them; and if they had but the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103239:28"/> leaſt pretence to give it out that the Party died in their Faith, they would wonderfully inſult over the Proteſtants. One Perſon dying, with whom Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of pains, and a Popiſh Prieſt alſo frequented that houſe, who was ſo vexed that he could not prevail with the Party, that he writ ſome Quaeries for Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> to anſwer; which he did ſo acutely and ſolidly, that the Ignorant Prieſt was netled and puzzled, and ſent to one of their more learned Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to vindicate their deſperate and falling Cauſe; he made a large Rejoynder, with abundance of Quotations out of the Ancients. To which Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> made a learned and ſufficient Reply; only was lame becauſe he had not by him the Authors Quoted; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſent the Papers to Mr. <hi>Illing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> (an excellent Scholar, and at that time much converſant in the Colledge Library at <hi>Mancheſter)</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:103239:28"/> who took abundance of pains to ſearch and read over ſome large Volumes to ſatisfie and ſolve a Quotation which referred not to Book, Chapter, or Page; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they joining together, that work was incomparably done, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of an Impreſſion; but to this day they heard no more of that Gentleman (for ſo the Popiſh Prieſts are called) though he had often to do with them.</p>
            <p>Another paſſage he writ in a Letter, dated <hi>June</hi> 12. 1675. to this purpoſe: I do juſt nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, either publickly or privately; it's much worſe with me, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Indulgence; yet God hath of late employed me another way (not ſo delightful and according to my genius, as Preaching): A Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman inclined to Marry a Popiſh Gentleman, would not Marry till ſhe had ſatisfaction that it was Lawful from ſome Divine; and pitch'd on me to reſolve the caſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103239:29"/> which I did very freely and plainly to her once or twice; I never dealt ſo plainly with any perſon in my life, and yet ſhe took all well; whereas ſhe fell out with her near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Relations and beſt Friends for ſpeaking but a little againſt it. She would needs have my Reaſons in writing, and having got them in a large diſſuaſive Letter, ſhe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the Gentleman, and he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it to a Prieſt; and twelve days after the Letter, brought me a long and ſubtle Anſwer; to which I made a large and (I think) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Reply. In the mean time we endeavoured to divert her to other Matches, but all in vain, her affections were too ſtrong for her judgment, though ſhe ſeem'd to approve and conſent to my Reply, yet went on with the Gentleman, and was juſt at Marriage; ſo that I could expect no other fruits of my labour in it, but my own ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that I had done my duty, leaving
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:103239:29"/> the event to God; God appear'd in the Mount. One Mr. <hi>D.</hi> (an hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful young Gentleman, of Religious Parents in <hi>Cheſhire)</hi> coming very accidentally to <hi>A.</hi> and finding this <hi>L.</hi> there, was ſtruck with Love, Courted her, and Married her in eight days time. Such a Providence muſt not paſs without particular notice, and ſpecial praiſe to God. The young Gentleman came thither alſo for a diverſion, upon the like occaſion; yet knowing nothing of her, but deſigning another place, was turned by a Miniſter in his company to take a night's lodging at <hi>A.</hi> This is the talk and wonder of the whole Countrey, the ſhame and confuſion of the Papiſts (who had a deſign upon that Family, and were confident it was their own) the joy of all good Proteſtants, and of all Friends to that Worſhipful Family. I want and crave your help to give due Praiſe to God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103239:30"/> for anſwering Prayers ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>Another thing which greatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated the Popiſh Party, was a ſharp and mettle Sermon Mr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> preach'd upon <hi>November</hi> 5. 1673. at <hi>Scaresbrick</hi> Chappel, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. 4. a very learned ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Diſcourſe againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; which (together with the forementioned provocations) did ſo offend them, that (though they could not take full revenge on him themſelves, yet) prevailed with ſome Juſtices to Proſecute him. And this is thought to be the true reaſon of all that unparallel'd rage of ſome againſt Mr. <hi>Heywood;</hi> whereas ſeveral others in the ſame circumſtances as culpable, were let alone to enjoy their Meetings quietly.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of theſe imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and oppoſitions, God was pleaſed to lay a very afflictive di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper upon his Body, which for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103239:30"/> a long time was judged to be the Stone or Gravel; certainly it was exceeding acute and painful; yet it is diſputable whether his loſs of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Liberties, or his violent Bodily Diſtemper, was the greater Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him. His Riding about Six or Seven Miles in the year 1675. ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his pain in making Water ſcarce tolerable; thus he writes: I have now this laſt ill fit diſcovered more of the cauſe of it than ever before: I am very confident it is not the Stone, but Flegm, or a Salt Humour, or both, that ſtops the Urine, <hi>&amp;c.—</hi>It's not properly the Strangury (ſaith he in another) but a Coagulation of Humours through overmuch Acidity, that ſharpens, and ſometimes ſtops my Urine,—Want of Health and Liberty (believe me) are two ſore evils; I hope you will parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly help me with your Prayers for direction as to Health, but more eſpecially as to reſtoration of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103239:31"/> in my beloved work; the loſs of which is a greater grief, than the want of Health and Eaſe. In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letter, dated <hi>July</hi> 15. 1676. he ſaith: I have endured extreame pain and torment a Month together, all which time (excepting two or three days) I never make Water (and that I was forced to do very often) but the laſt drop came out with ſo much difficulty, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive pain (about the neck of the Bladder) that it made me roar and tremble, and had ſo ſhrunk my Fleſh, and weakened my Body, that I did apprehend Death to be approaching: The good Lord fit and prepare me for it, and account me worthy to find Mercy in that time of need,—My pain was occaſioned by the great heat, and preaching that hot weather oftener and longer than I was well able,—I am ſure I have greateſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſubmit to his holy Will, yea, and be thankful alſo, that though
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103239:31"/> he hath afflicted me very ſore, yet he hath not given me over to death; whereas I hear of many that are dead of late of my diſtemper (Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> Couſin <hi>John Cromp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and ſeveral hereabouts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe two months). I beg your prayers, that if God ſpare my Life, he would alſo give Health and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to improve it in his ſervice, more publickly and fruitfully; or if it be death (which will be leſs unwelcome, becauſe of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints, pangs, and troubles in this world, only my Wife and Children make the thoughts of it burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) may God be glorified, I hope it will be my advantage,—I wiſh neither you nor any faithful Miniſter, that minds and loves his work, may ever know what I have felt in the want of People and Work: Other Afflictions are light, compared to a dumb Mouth, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sabbaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:103239:32"/>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, he had a wonderful great deſire, once again, if it were the Will of God, to viſit his friends in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> and God was pleaſed to grant his requeſt; for he gave him ſome mitigation of his Pain, which was an encouragement to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that Journey; ſo himſelf, his Wife, and his Two Sons, Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into <hi>Yorkſhire, April</hi> 20. 1677. there he preach'd the Sermons that are ſince Printed; and another moſt excellent and pathetical Sermon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 8. From thence he ſent his Eldeſt Son to be trained up in Academical Learning, with Mr. <hi>Frankland</hi> at <hi>Natland</hi> in <hi>Weſtmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But Oh! what affectionate parting was there! as if they muſt never ſee one another's faces again; (and indeed ſo it proved) they could not ſpeak to each other for weeping and ſobbing; he deſired another to pray, for he could not refrain: In that Journey he was
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:103239:32"/> carried out beyond himſelf in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preaching, diſcourſing, to the admiration and edification of all his ancient Friends in thoſe Parts, though he had frequent returns of his wonted Pain: He was as a man coming down from Heaven to tell what's done there; or as one ripe for Heaven, too big for Earth, upon the wing to take his flight into thoſe Manſions above, as indeed it proved.</p>
            <p>After he had done his work in thoſe Parts which he deſigned, he left <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> on <hi>May</hi> 1. 1677. but could reach that day but Ten Miles; the next morning he went to <hi>Ratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal;</hi> he was forcibly detained by the importunity of Chriſtian Friends, and preached there that evening, tho greatly to his prejudice as to Health; the day following he reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bolton;</hi> yet, ſaith he, with great difficulty and hard hewing, they got home on Friday night; and it would have been great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103239:33"/> to have ſtaid one day longer, upon ſeveral neceſſary accounts, which he mentions. Thus God carried him abroad in Mercy, and brought him ſeaſonably back to his own houſe in ſafety.</p>
            <p>How much he was ſatisfied with this Journey (though his pains were extreme ſeveral days after his return home), his Letter, <hi>May</hi> 14. 1677. doth teſtifie: The great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (ſaith he) in my late Journey to you, comforts with you, and ſafe return home (where we found all well), I hope I ſhall never forget: pray help me to be thankful for them.—I do heartily thank you for all your Pulpit, Table, Houſe, and Countrey-kindneſs,—I am ſorry and aſhamed I made no better improvement of them, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ever I ſhall enjoy ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities again, of doing my ſelf and others good in your parts; but an indiſpoſed Body and a bad heart, marr Duties and waſte Mercies.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:103239:33"/>
            <p>His diſtemper ſtill continued and prevailed upon him all that Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; in a Letter dated <hi>September</hi> 20. 1677. he ſaith:—I am far from being well; and as the Church once complained, ſhe forgat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; ſo I health, and am ready ſometimes to add (as She) my ſtrength and my hope is periſhed from the Lord. This day Five Weeks I came from the Exerciſe at <hi>Toxtoth-Park,</hi> where I had preached twice, and oftener then I was well able a little before: Since that day I never came on Horſe-back, nor preached but once near home; but all this time God hath been preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me with a terrible thundring Voice; Oh! that I could hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it! So ſharp, and ſo long a fit of Pain, I never had ſince this diſtemper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun.—God alone knows what may be the iſſue of it; but for my part, though I find it no eaſy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to look death in the face, and to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103239:34"/> conquer the difficulties that precede and attend it; yet I have no great reaſon to love life, or to deſire my long ſtay in this wicked weary world; my pained days and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome nights, make thoughts of death and grave leſs terrible, and apprehenſions of Reſt with Chriſt moſt welcome and pleaſant. But I feel natural inclinations working towards life, and to loving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the fair glaſs of doing God more and better Service in his Church. I am beſt reſolved, and moſt at Anchor, when I can (but oh! how ſeldom! how coldly! do I) ſay, The Will of the Lord be done. Dear Brother, Pray for me, (as I would do for my ſelf) that to me to live may be Chriſt and to die gain. Yeſterday for ſome hours I was in extreme torment, but am much eaſier, I bleſs God, to day; but my pain is not in the ſame manner as formerly, but liker an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in the Bladder, which makes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103239:34"/> my diſeaſe more dangerous, as well as painful,—it is the Lord's mercy I am not utterly conſumed, that I can ſit thus long to write to you, which many times, I cannot, but I am now weary with it.</p>
            <p>The laſt Letter (ſo far as I can find) was by him dated <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. 1677. which I ſhall moſtly tranſcribe:</p>
            <p>My dear Brother, this evening I received yours, for which I thank you; it breathes nothing but love and comfort to me; Oh! how ſweet! how ſeaſonable! love in you, Oh! how tender! Eſpecially I thank you for your prayers, and the prayers of others by your means; I account them a precious treaſure, and the ſureſt and ſpeedieſt remedy in all troubles. Oh! pray again, who knows but that may prevail when nothing elſe can! I have been ſenſibly better ſince that day of your tears and groans. But who am I that any ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103239:35"/> for me? A poor, weak, uſeleſs wretch, nothing, and leſs than nothing. I have been long, in regard of work, in God's Vineyard, a withered branch, a dry ſtick, and now my body is withered like the graſs, my skin parched, my moiſture dried up through extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of pain, which hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nine or ten weeks, day and night. About a Month ago, friends ſeeing death in my face and looks, they prevailed with me to ſend for Dr. <hi>Grundy,</hi> who found me in a languiſhing condition, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome hope: He told me, my diſtemper was not the Stone, nor Ulcer in the Bladder (which I feared becauſe of my ſharp pains and ſoreneſs) but a Dyſuria; my Blood was vitiated, my moiſture ſowre, and there wanted due ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Serum from the Blood; that it would require much time and patience to bring the Body to a good ſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For ſince I have
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103239:35"/> been taking one ſort or other of Phyſick; and am now taking a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et-drink for the Scurvey, which, I think, hath done me moſt good, but ſtill my pain continues, though not altogether ſo acute, as at the firſt, but I have very weary reſtleſs nights; many times I am conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to get up and walk two or three hours, but God ſupports, his word comforts in all, and over all, his ways are mercy and truth, it is his mercy that I am not conſumed; yea, 'tis mercy and faithfulneſs that I am afflicted, I have reaſon to ſay I could not have been without; nay, I would not have been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this trial for an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if God pleaſe to ſpare my life, and reſtore ſtrength, I hope others will find that I have gained conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably by this Sea-adventure,—I am your indebted and endeared Brother, <hi>N. Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His diſtempers growing thus up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, gradually wore away and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103239:36"/> weaken'd his body, and took out the pins and pluck'd down the ſtakes of his frail tabernacle; he wore away inſenſibly, his friends ſeeing he had ſtrength to walk, did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his end ſo near, as indeed it proved On <hi>Thurſday, Decemb.</hi> 13. 1677. they perceived him to alter, and grow ſomething worſe than he had been, not ſo much in the violence of pain, as in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Spirits, and falling into drowzineſs and ſlumbering; that very day, he ſaid, with tears run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his face, that he could willingly die if it were the next hour, but for the good of the Church, and his poor Wife and Children, and with them he could be content to live, were it in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. That night being ready to go to Bed, he ſate down in his Chair, and looking up towards Heaven, moved his eyes very much, his Wife asked him, How he did? but he could not anſwer, as ſhe ſuppoſed; but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:103239:36"/> ſoon after he ſaid he would go to Bed; being got to Bed, he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like Trance, and lay for a while ſpeechleſs; being better, he looked about him, and ſaw them weeping, and ſaid, if you knew Chriſt better, this carnal affection would ceaſe, and natural would be ſanctified, and run in a ſpiritual channel: Oh! learn to know Chriſt more! for my own part, I have preached Chriſt all my Life, and I bleſs God with good ſucceſs: It's common with many now-a-days to have baſe and low thoughts of Chriſt, and his imputed righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but if I had twenty lives to live, I would ſpend them all in that work.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Friday,</hi> a Kinſman that was come from <hi>London</hi> viſited him, but he was ſo weak and liſtleſs, that he was very unfit for converſe; and indeed at the beſt he was ſparing in diſcourſe; he uſed to ſpeak little, but what he ſpake was very
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:103239:37"/> pithy, pertinent, and ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> night, Mr. <hi>Starky,</hi> a Reverend and Godly Miniſter, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited him; he asked him, Whether it was any trouble to him that he did not Conform? He anſwered, No, it's a great comfort to me; this he ſpake with much chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, adding ſome more words to evidence his ſatisfaction in what he had done and ſuffered: Mr. <hi>Starky</hi> asked him, What Promiſes he could now rely upon, or what Scripture-paſſages ſupported him? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>For to me to live is Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>and to die gain. Chriſt hath loved me, and given himſelf for me.</hi> He <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> was frequently repeating thoſe words, <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly,—.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About four hours before he died, being asked how he did? he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, very well.—His laſt words that he was heard to utter, were, <hi>Come away, Lord, come, come,—</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:103239:37"/> and ſo he breathed out his bleſſed Soul; on the Lord's-day morning, <hi>Dec.</hi> 6. 1677. about nine a Clock; ſo God made the day of his hard and ſore labour, the day of his entrance into his Eternal Reſt.</p>
            <p>And 'tis worthy obſervation, that God hath drawn off many eminent Miniſters, and choice Chriſtians from the ſtage of this World, near or upon that day: This Holy day of heavenly Reſt hath commenced upon them the everlaſting day of Reſt in Heaven. Chriſt's Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction-day hath been their Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion day: They parted with this jarring Muſick on Earth, to be join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that coeleſtial Choire above. This our Brother often made melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in his heart (though he was not very tunable in his voice below;) now the high Praiſes of God are ſounded by him, and at the Great day Soul and Body ſhall make a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious Conſort in that Bleſſed Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:103239:38"/>
            <p>And now this Holy, Learned, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Man of God is advanced above guilt, corruption, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and perſecution, pains of Body, fears of Spirit, diſturbances in God's Worſhip, Impriſonments, Confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Baniſhments: Oh what a bleſſed State have they above taken poſſeſſion of! happy Souls, that are ſafely lodged in the Arms of their Dear Redeemer! It were worth the while to ſtand ſtill and take a view of the Spirits made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23.</note> in the other World.</p>
            <p>Let us only glance a little on their privative and poſitive Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 3, 4, 5. 1. <hi>There ſhall be no more curſe, [i. e.</hi> no more fruits of God's diſpleaſure upon man for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, nor cauſeleſs Curſe by mens unjuſt Cenſures.] 2. <hi>But the throne of God, and the lamb ſhall be in it;</hi> [this is the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Viſion, that looks Souls out of ſin and ſuffering, and who dare preſume to arreſt the King's Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:103239:38"/> in his preſence? 3. <hi>And his ſervants ſhall ſerve him,</hi> [whether Devils or Men will or no, theſe bleſſed Attendants on the King of Glory, ſhall never be interrupted in their chearful Service.] 4. <hi>And</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12. 1 John 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall ſee his face; [i. e.</hi> they ſhall not <hi>behold him in a glaſs dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as now they ſee God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>but</hi> then <hi>face to face;</hi> yea, <hi>they ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> (which is a riddle to us here below) imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, though not comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively.] 5. <hi>And his name ſhall be in their fore-heads; [i. e.</hi> They ſhall openly profeſs whoſe they are, and to whom they belong, as diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht palpably from wicked men, and Hypocrites: They ſhall no more ſculk in Corners, or be thruſt out of publick Places, but ſhall openly avouch their Maſter.] 6 <hi>And there ſhall be no night there; [i. e.</hi> no works of darkneſs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or conteſt with; no Beaſts of prey to creep forth and worry
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:103239:39"/> the Saints; no ſecret Plots againſt them, no ignorance amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Societies to create Differences, Jealouſies and Animoſities.] 7. <hi>They need no candle, neither light of the ſun;</hi> [no need of Ordinances, as here below they are uſed, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Preachers ſhall ſtudy or preach no more; People need not hear Sermons, neither Preachers or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſtand in need of Seals, the Subſtance is preſent, Shadows flee away.] 8. <hi>The Lord God giveth them light;</hi> [their injoyment of God is immediate, uninterrupted and ſatisfying; in his light they ſee light; as the Object will be clearer to be ſeen, ſo their Eyes will be perfectly irradiated to behold him] 9. <hi>And they ſhall reign for ever and ever;</hi> [though his Servants ſhall ſerve him, yet it ſhall be no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome bondage or ſlavery, but a liberty and dominion; they ſhall ſit with Chriſt in his Throne as Aſſeſſors, judge the World, and (it <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 2.</note>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:103239:39"/> may be) judge their Judges; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the righteous Sentence of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 2.</note> their Royal Maſter the Bleſſed Jeſus, <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords.]</hi> And if all this be meant of ſome glorious ſtate of the Church on Earth (as ſome will needs have it) yet that's but a faint reſemblance of this more happy State in Heaven: And further, for the duration of it, 'tis added: 10. <hi>And they ſhall reign for ever and ever;</hi> [Earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs are but ſhort-liv'd King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, have their periods, but Kings are of leſs continuance; of Chriſt's Kingdom there is no end, and his Subjects reign runs paralel with the Life of God, and Line of Eternity.] Oh bleſſed Souls, oh happy Saints, that ſhall for ever be with the Lord! And here we leave the Soul of our dear Brother, ſinging triumphantly the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Lamb, in the height of <hi>Zion;</hi> whilſt we poor Mortals are glad if we can ſing but the Song of degrees.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:103239:40"/>
            <p>As for the ſolemn interment of that Caſe and Cabinet, once the Receptacle, now the Relict of that precious Pearl; it was judged meet that Solemnity ſhould be put off till <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> Dec. 19. 1677. that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Friends might have ſeaſonable notice; and that day Mr. <hi>Starky,</hi> a Non-conformiſt Miniſter, preached an excellent Sermon in the Pariſh-Church at <hi>Ormes-kirk</hi> (no man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding him; nay all that were any way concerned, conſenting) upon <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>When Chriſt, who is our life, ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in glory.</hi> There was a vaſt confluence of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at his Funeral, great lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many ſignal demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of univerſal love and reſpect, which he had from all the Country; his Body was laid in the Chancel, and Burying-place, which belongs to the Ancient Family of <hi>Stanlies</hi> of <hi>Bickerſtaff,</hi> Knights and Baronets; it was with their free conſent and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:103239:40"/> deſire. The Reverend Miniſter that preached, after he had acutely, learnedly, and profitably handled his Text, gave a ſhort, but full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him, in his ſeveral Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, as Miniſter, Husband, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Friend, and eſpecially God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as a Chriſtian: And as the Eccho's of the Hearers gave teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth of what was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſo to their ſad reſentment of their irreparable loſs. All the Town, in their ſeveral Capacities, doing him honour in their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar way: Mr. Conſtable (the chiefeſt Officer in the Town, of conſiderable Authority) carried the Staff (like a Mace) before the Corps, and the reſt walked in their due and decent order.</p>
            <p>Now although this was inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant to the Dead, and not edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much to the Living, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Burials have always amongſt civilized Nations been accounted the duty of the Living, and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:103239:41"/> to the Dead: And there is a ſpecial remembrance of this in Scripture; for it's ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that all <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did him honour at his death: On the contrary, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded <note place="margin">2 Chron. 32. 33.</note> as a perpetual Infamy of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam</hi> (the bad Son of good <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 21. 20.</note>) that he departed without being deſir'd; and of another bad Son of a good King, <hi>(Jehoiakin,</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſiah)</hi> that they ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, <hi>Ah my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,—</hi>but he ſhall be buried with <note place="margin">Jer. 22. 18, 19.</note> the burial of an Aſs, drawn and caſt forth beyond the Gates of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> But this Good man honoured God whilſt living, and God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him at his death; and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced his Soul to better, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Honour.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> went to his Grave in peace, after all his tumultuous Toſſings upon the tempeſtuous Sea of this World; he dyed in the 44th year of his Age, and about two
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103239:41"/> Months above, having lived long in a little time; and I find ſeveral choice men taken out of the world about that Age. So among the <hi>German</hi> Divines, <hi>Strigelius</hi> dyed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. vit. in</hi> Metch. Ad.</note> 44 years of Age, and 6 months; <hi>Flinſchpach</hi> 44. <hi>Simlerus</hi> dyed in the 45th year; ſo we find <hi>Erpenius</hi> dyed at 40 years of age; Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Rollock</hi> dyed in the 43d year of his age; the Famous Dr. <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> in his 47th. But to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more, our Famous Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Perkins</hi> lived but 44 years, being cut off by a violent Fit of the Stone.</p>
            <p>And indeed we have frequently obſerved, that laborious Miniſters are ſhort-liv'd; ſome are of weak Conſtitutions, and ſpend their Lungs with ſpeaking; or by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentary life contract Diſeaſes, or are fretted with the untowardneſs of their people; or God in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment takes them away as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a wicked world: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:103239:42"/> like a Candle they ſpend themſelves to give light to others. Many gracious young men are very zealous, and make haſt with their Work, and get it quickly diſpatcht off their hands, and go to bed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times: And God is not willing to be without their company too long. Oh how many brave promiſing Plants have been pluckt up of late years, that were heavy laden with choice Fruits; whilſt ſome old wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Trees, barren and fruitleſs, ſtill ſtand cumbering the ground! But the Soveraign <hi>Jehovah</hi> knows what is fitteſt, and doth all things well.</p>
            <p>A little while before Mr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> dyed, he ſaid to a Friend, I think this turning out of our Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Places will coſt Mr. <hi>Yates</hi> and me our Lives. Oh this goes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily! our caſting out of our great Places was not ſo much as caſting us out of our little Places: And indeed Mr. <hi>Yates</hi> of <hi>Warrington</hi> dyed ſhortly after.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:103239:42"/>
            <p>Having thus nakedly given a brief account of Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi>'s Birth, Life, Imployment and Death, and what is worthy a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark therein; I ſhall ſelect ſome few Characters of him, comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to, and imitable by his ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Brethren, Friends and Hearers; for the Memory of the Juſt is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and poſſibly Generations yet to come may reap benefit by what they find recorded of him. And I dare appeal to the God of Truth, that ſearcheth hearts, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription I ſhall give of him is true, which I have by perſonal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or credible Teſtimony.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to his Proportion, Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy, and Conſtitution, which is the Caſe, Shell, and Outſide, that was comely enough, no part lacking, crooked, or deformed; tall, and ſtraight, blackiſh curled Hair; not fat, nor very lean, yet fatter in his Body than he ſeemed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:103239:43"/> by his Face; of an healthful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution moſtly after he was paſt his Childhood; which might have continued long, had not the Veſſel been crackt by impetuous daſhings, inflamed with the love of God, and zeal for Souls, which haled the Carcaſe faſter than Nature could keep pace; and this over-driving took off the Chariot-wheels; for all agreed, that his exceſſive pains laid the foundation of theſe Diſeaſes, that at laſt waſted his Spirits: He was an excellent Footman, and could walk both faſt and far, and in his laſt Diſtemper walked much, and found moſt eaſe therein; tho when he went beyond his ſtrength, it coſt him dear. In his beſt health he was an extraordinary Sweater, eſpecially in his preaching; his ſweat hath dropt at his Hair-ends, wet his Band all over; Letters wet in his Pocket through Linings, as if put in water; and it may be that ſweating was ſome advantage to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:103239:43"/> him; but when he could not take that pains to ſweat, and thereby evaporate thoſe acid Humors, they might ſettle, and gather into thoſe acute Diſeaſes: Yet want of leiſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cooling might prejudice him. Once old Mr. <hi>Woods</hi> and he preacht an Exerciſe in a Chappel in an hot Summer-day, the number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was too many to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hearing; Mr. <hi>Haywood</hi> having preacht firſt, Mr. <hi>Woods</hi> withdrew the Army, or Aſſembly, from that ſtrong-hold wherein they were coopt, into the Champaign of a fair large Field, where that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, Solid, Laborious Man of God preacht under a ſhady Tree; Mr. <hi>Haywood</hi> ſitting in a Chair, got an extream Cold, which coſt him dear afterward.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to his natural Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Diſpoſition, he was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Cholerick, being of a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Compexion; but ſuch was the predominancy of Grace, that it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:103239:44"/> did very little appear in him, being regulated and rectified with that ſweet corrective of Gods Fear, which turned his natural Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a Spiritual Channel, and put a due by as into it, to move God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: He was much tranſported in the affection of love, where Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon dictated a diſcovery of the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of the Object, both in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals and Naturals. In his younger days he was judged to be inclined to Melancholy, ſitting ſometimes ſilent, and poring upon ſomething; and ſo he was in his laſt Diſtemper: Yet at ſome times he was very chearful, and facetious, putting off harmleſs Jeſts with much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for his own and his Friends diverſion; and this, (with recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating himſelf with his Children) was all the recreation that he uſed for many years. He was indeed won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful witty and ingenious, when he ſlacked the ſtrings a little, and applied himſelf that way, which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:103239:44"/> was very rarely; his mind being ordinarily intent upon more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary buſineſs in his Study, or Soul concerns.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to his Entrance into the Miniſtry, and his Judgment in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Points, he was (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Education) a ſtrict Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, as they are called, avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both the extremes of Prelatical Tyranny on the one hand, and Congregational. Democracy on the other. Upon his firſt ſetling at <hi>Ormiskirk</hi> he preſently applied himſelf to the Miniſters of that Claſſe in that Diviſion where God had caſt his Lot; and after proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and approbation of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Abilities, Learning, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for that Place, conſent of the People expreſſed—he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſet apart by Faſting and Prayer, and impoſition of Hands, to the work of the Miniſtry, in a Publick Congregation, to the great ſatisfaction of all that were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:103239:45"/> The Reverend grave Miniſters that laid hands on him, were Mr. <hi>Thomas Johnſon,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Halſal;</hi> Mr. <hi>Thompſon,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Sefton;</hi> Mr. <hi>Edward Gee,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Eccleſton;</hi> Mr. <hi>Bell</hi> of <hi>Highton;</hi> all Worthy, Eminent Men; and ſome others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to his Miniſterial Labours, I ſhall add little to what hath been ſaid: He willingly did ſpend, and was ſpent in the Service of his Lord and Maſter; he prayed and wept, preached and ſweat in publick and private, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; he conſtantly preached twice a day, catechiſed, exhorting, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing with all long-ſuffering: He was much in ſpending days in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Faſting and Prayer with Chriſtian Friends in his Pariſh, and elſewhere. He loved and delighted in the Communion of Saints; ſo that thoſe few Chriſtians in thoſe parts lamentably bewail the loſs of him as their Paſtor and Leader,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:103239:45"/> their prompter to, and prop in thoſe ſpiritual Exerciſes. His heart was ſet to do good unto all, but his delight was in God's Children. He refuſed not to come and viſit the pooreſt and wickedeſt, that either ſent for him, or that he judged would make him welcome, or where he had any hopes of doing good. He was diligent in viſiting the ſick, and took great pains with the ignorant, procuring Catechiſms for them that were willing to learn, inſtructing them, and uſing inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious artifices to bring them into a love of Religion, and engaging young people to learn.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He was exceeding meek and patient, not only in bearing his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily pains with an invincible ſpirit; but enduring the affronts, reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and various indignities that were offered him, with an heroick chearfulneſs; yea, he gloried in them as the afflictions of Chriſt, notwithſtanding all the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:103239:46"/> oppoſitions; yet his Spirit was ſo ſweetly calmed, that none ever heard him revile or ſpeak evil of the Inſtruments, but many have heard him pity and pray for them; it's true, his Spirit was ſometimes ſo diſturbed, that he would dream of them, and mention them in his ſleep; but ſtill he bore a compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate heart towards them, and would often bewail their condition; though ſome of the Townſmen, and others, thought ſome Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were malicious and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not fit to be named; yet he freely forgave all, as an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf, and affectionately prayed for their repentance and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their ſin againſt God; oft ſaying, If this or that be the worſt they can do, we ſhall ſhift well enough: He had in ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able degree, learned that hard leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon our Lord teacheth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 44. <hi>But I ſay unto you, love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:103239:46"/> 
               <hi>them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you.</hi> This, this, is a great height of true Chriſtianity, to do good, and hear evil, bear our Croſs, and follow Chriſt with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and ſelf-denial.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He was very faithful to his Friends, and look'd upon the bond of friendſhip as ſacred, and not to be violated, whether in the buſineſs of counſelling, and keeping ſecrets, or preſerving, and performing the truſt repoſed in him, and this was not ſmall, nor from perſons incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, and this upon ſeveral ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, putting himſelf to much coſt, many troubles, and ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, rather than ſeem by negligence to falſify his word, or in any reſpect to fail of his duty; as many inſtances might manifeſt. It was Conſcience of his duty God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that awed his ſpirit in thoſe caſes wherein no mortal could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect or puniſh him for neglect. He
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:103239:47"/> was marvellous obliging in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment; very taking in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, with ſuch as he could be free with; inſtructing the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, indulging the impotent; by words or carriage manifeſting his diſlike of ſin, but encouraging any that diſcovered any ſparks of true Piety, however they might differ from him in ſome things; for he was of a Catholick Spirit.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He was very humble and ſelf-denying, which was the brave ornament of all his other graces and eminent qualifications; this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was his Maſter-piece, he had always very mean thoughts of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his own undertakings, diſguſting others commendations of him; which indeed were to him <hi>inſtar fulminis,</hi> like a thunderbolt, as that <hi>German</hi> Divine ſaid of mens praiſes; yea, he would even cover his face with ſhame, and modeſtly bluſh when any ſpoke well of him; his maxim was rather to be, than
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:103239:47"/> ſeem good; not affecting triumphs (as <hi>Pompey</hi> did) but approving his heart to God; being more pleaſed with God's gracious acceptance, and the conſcience of his own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, than affecting the favour of great ones, or the applauſe of the vulgar; tho there was ſcare any had ſuch general approbation, or flocking after them; yet his Spirit was not elated, or lifted up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: In him was verified that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, That honour is like a ſhadow, which being purſued, it flies away; and the more a man flies from it, the more it follows him. He could never be perſuaded to Print any of his labours, though he was often ſolicited thereto; for he judged nothing that he did worth expoſing to publick view; he ſo far diſliked the humour of oſtentation, that he abſtained from doing that which might have been profitable to the Church. Though his Sermons were elaborate and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:103239:48"/> acurate, yet very pathetical, which he deſired to be conveyed only to the ears and hearts of his hearers: Yea, his modeſty lock'd up his lips in company, unleſs he had a juſt call to ſpeak; and he ſpake with great judgment, and as much hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and ſubmiſſion to better judgments, but always with great advantage to his hearers. He was mild in his cenſure, and ſpake well of others mean and well-meaning undertakings; he commended all that in any thing were praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and envied them not that honour that was due to them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He was much and mighty in Prayer; he had an excellent gift in confeſſing ſin, petitioning for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and thankfulneſs to God for mercies received. He did with pat and proper Scripture-expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wreſtle with God in Prayer: Oh! how frequently and fervently did he pour out his Soul to the Lord with ſighs and groans, ſtrong cries
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:103239:48"/> and tears! He had a large meaſure of the Spirit of Adoption, and was uſually large, and much enlarged in that duty, eſpecially upon extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary occaſions; Though he had long uſed to go to God alone; yet in his laſt ſickneſs he was more abundant in Cloſet-Prayer: His Wife and Children coming to him, have often found him upon his knees: And the Lord gave in many ſignal impreſſions upon his Spirit, and remarkable returns of his prayers. Many years ago, when his Wife was dangerouſly ſick at <hi>Godley</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> nigh to death, he told her ſhe muſt not die at that time; ſhe demanded of him, Why he thought ſo? He anſwered, becauſe my heart is much enlarged in prayer to beg for thy life; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly God raiſed her up at that time. And he hath oft taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the frame of his Spirit in prayer for ſeveral ſick perſons; and hath taken his meaſures from his
<pb facs="tcp:103239:49"/> ſtraitneſs, or his enlargedneſs, and it hath often proved ſuitable to his preſages.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He had a great meaſure of Faith, both as to Soul-concerns, and temporal affairs. As to the former, God had helped in Soul-troubles to truſt God in the way of a promiſe, and at laſt buoyed up his Faith into a Plerophery or full Aſſurance. As to the latter, he was trained up in the life of Faith many years; a Wife, and nine ſmall Children, being turned out of all, having nothing before-hand, and knew not in an ordinary rational way, where his ſubſiſtence muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; this put his Faith hard to it: yet committing his all into God's hands, he was ſtrangely ſupplied, as if he had been fed by Ravens, or as <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs: <hi>O man! great was thy faith!</hi> O Lord! great was thy bounty! It's true, he was often afraid of diſcontent and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring; but pluck'd up his ſpirit,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:103239:49"/> ſaying to his Wife, Let us pray and wait on God, he never failed us yet, come let us truſt him; this he ſpake with great alacrity; and he oft took notice, that at a pinch God ſent in ſeaſonable ſupply by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected means; help came in ſo ſtrangely, that he reſolved to ſet down punctually what he received, and of whom. He ſaid once to a Friend, I cannot but wonder how God ſends in Money juſt as I need it, he drops it into my hand by Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and Shillings moſt ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; and the review of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments much ſtrengthens my Faith, and engageth me to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: This courſe he had taken for above twelve years, and advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Friend to the ſame courſe. From his multiplied experiments he gathered great encouragements; he often wondered at the unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable proviſion God made for him and his.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:103239:50"/>
            <p n="10"> 10. He was of a loving, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able frame, much addicted to peace, both in Sacreds and Civils: He was not willing to fall out with any, and it was ſtrange if any fell out with him, for he gave not any juſt occaſion at any time. Teſtimonies and inſtances might be produced wherein he complied to the utmoſt extent of what he judged lawful, to avoid giving any offence, and ſometimes receded from his right, for peace ſake. It is true he was a man of contention, as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was, but it was his grief, and made him cry, Wo is me! and beſides, it was rather paſſively than actively that he was ſo; men contended with him, rather than he with them, and it was in the matters of his God and Conſcience; and he was reſolved rather to obey and pleaſe God than men: In this he was as a ſturdy Oak, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:103239:50"/> matters a bending Ozier. If any time he was angry at others, yet anger did not ferment into malice, or long reſt in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; he ſought reconciliation with them; and if any had taken of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at him, he ſought to win them by loving means and methods of kindneſs; yea, he was not only a peace-keeper, but a peace-maker to his power, reconciling Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that were at diſtance; not by ſitting with them in the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe (as the manner of ſome is) but by Chriſtian Advice, Counſel, Prayers, healing differences in God's way. He preached an excellent Sermon upon mutual Love from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 2. an excellent duty from an excellent pattern, excellently managed, diſcovering a ſavoury ſpirit, full of gentleneſs, ſobriety, moderation; he ſought to calm mens minds, and lay the wind of paſſion, that the word might take place; for <hi>the fruit of righteouſneſs</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:103239:51"/> 
               <hi>is ſown in peace of them that make peace.</hi> James 3. 18.</p>
            <p n="11">11. But tho he was of a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpirit to condeſcend to any thing lawful for peace ſake, yet not ſo facile, flexible, and wire-drawn as to recede an hairs breadth from truth, or well fixed principles; he was <hi>[Magnes &amp; Adamas]</hi> an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive Loadſtone, yet an inflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Adamant in the cauſe of God. He well underſtood his own latitude, and as he would not groundleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdraw by wanton curioſity, ſo he would not be led aſide into ſin to pleaſe a friend, or proſtitute his Conſcience to mens fancy: Others might perhaps judge it a needleſs preciſeneſs, perverſeneſs, or obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy; but he could not turn his ſails to their wind, or dance after their pipes, though he had manifold temptations on all hands from great and ſmall; but he was of bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi>'s mind and practice, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>To whom we gave place by ſubjection,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:103239:51"/> 
               <hi>no not for an hour; that the truth of the Goſpel might continue with you.</hi> And if he died not a Martyr for, yet a Confeſſor of, and Witneſs to, the truths that concern Chriſts Kingly Office over his Church, to appoint what Laws, Orders, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Ordinances, he pleaſeth, as one of his laſt Sermons abundantly doth demonſtrate: He was Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto death, and now receives a Crown life. It might be ſaid of this man of God, as was ſaid of <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Sarcerius, [Lucebat in hoc viro</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Melch Ad. <hi>Vit. Sarc. p.</hi> 326.</note> 
               <hi>commemorabilis gravitas &amp; conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, non minas, non exilia, non ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam ullius hominis potentiam aut vim pertimeſcebat: Pene dixerim, ſolem facilius de curſa dimoveri potuiſſe, quam Eraſmum à veritatis profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione].</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. He made great proficiency daily both in Learning, Grace, and Holineſs; having laid a low foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, he built a ſtately viſible ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure: It might be ſaid of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:103239:52"/> him, as the Apoſtle of the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, That his faith did grow exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and his love to chriſtians abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> The Pearl grew too big for the ſhell; his head ſoared above the Clouds, and his heart mounted Heavenwards. And as he grew in Faith, Love, Meekneſs, Zeal for God, Endearedneſs to Souls; ſo above all, in Humility, Self-denial, and Contempt of the World; as he travelled up and down to do good, ſo he travelled in birth over poor neceſſitous ſinners. Poſſibly ſome may think Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> took too much upon him, and was too ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in his indefatigable pains, both in the face of danger, and to the hazard of his health; but as to the one, <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Apology was his, <hi>[Would you have me found idle when my Lord cometh?]</hi> As to the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, his Anſwer and Actings were juſtifiable by a like inſtance in the life of <hi>Olevian,</hi> who asked them, Whether he muſt ſuſpend, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percede
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:103239:52"/> his Preaching at that time for fear of danger? Or, Whether they deſired to hear him as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? The People all with hands lifted up, and loud voices cryed out <hi>[Imo hoc, imo hoc, &amp; per Deum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Melch Ad. <hi>Vit.</hi> Olev. <hi>p.</hi> 600.</note> 
               <hi>te oramus, ut pergas concionari]</hi> We beſeech thee to Preach. Thus the neceſſities and importunity of the People extorted work from this poor man; His heart was upon it, and being engaged, he regarded not any carnal arguments from fleſh and blood, or ſelf-preſervation. The laſt Sermon he preached at a Friends houſe in the Pariſh, was as a Swan-like Song, pithy, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, ardent and affectionate; that as before he exceeded others, ſo then he exceeded himſelf; as if he knew before hand that it was the laſt. Thus his laſt was more than his firſt; and the nearer the center, the quicker was his motion: He was ſo full of matter, as if he were at a loſs for time to do the remaind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:103239:53"/> of his work in, that he might diſpatch it all and be at Reſt.</p>
            <p n="13">13. He was very Charitable to the Poor, and ſuch as were in real Neceſſity. And though his ſmall Revenue, and conſtant Charge, did ſomewhat bind his hands, yet could not reſtrain his Spirit; he drew out his Soul to the Hungry. And indeed <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12.</note> true Charity is ſeated rather in a large heart than liberal hand; the <hi>Imprimis</hi> of a willing mind finds acceptance, when the <hi>Items</hi> of Alms run but ſhallow. And to his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <note place="margin">v. 3.</note> many will bear him record; yea, beyond his power he was will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; freely welcoming objects of pitty, ſtirring up his hearers to free Contributions, eſpecially in the behalf of Godly Poor, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the bowels of many were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed by this Brother. And hence it was that he that ſowed <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 6.</note> bountifully, did then (and much more doth now) reap bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; <hi>For the liberal ſoul ſhall be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 25.</note>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:103239:53"/> 
               <hi>made fat; and he that watereth, ſhall be watered alſo himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. He was a great admirer, and a profound Preacher of the glorious Goſpel-deſign, eſpecially in the giving of Chriſt. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this he made his [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] the main ſcope of all his preaching. It's true, he did oft preach Law and Terror to awaken mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and drive them out of themſelves to Chriſt. He did often preſs duty in a circumſpect, exact, and holy walking; and urged a ſpiritual, and diligent worſhipping of God: But ſtill demonſtrating, that Chriſt is the end of the Law <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 4.</note> for righteouſneſs to every one that believeth. It was his proper ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and moſt ſuitable to his Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Spirit to know and preach nothing but a crucified and glorified Redeemer. He much inlarged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 2.</note> upon the Goſpel-way of the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of a Sinner, by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſt's perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:103239:54"/> by faith: His working thoughts run ſtill upon this Theam, ſleeping and waking; ſo that once (many years ago) he was heard in his Dream to ſay [there are vaſt heaps of Free-grace]: His heart was greatly inamour'd with the love of God in ſending Chriſt; as appeared to the content, profit, and wonder of many, by a Sermon he preached the ſame year he died upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 8. This was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Element in which he moved: And few dived that depth into that <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 19.</note> unfathomable Ocean of this Love that paſſeth knowledge, as he did.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He was a zealous Defender of Truth, and Impugner of Errors; he did ſtrenuouſly <hi>contend for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> 
               <hi>faith once delivered to the ſaints:</hi> He much delighted in the form of wholeſome words, and loved not new-coin'd phraſes, which are apt to amuſe mens minds, and inſtil into them poiſonous Principles: He lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and uſed ſound ſpeech that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:103239:54"/> be condemned, as well as ſound and orthodox Truth; ſtanding at an equal diſtance from <hi>Arminians</hi> on one hand, and <hi>Antinomians</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He had a ſtrange ſagacity in diſcerning Perſons, Things and Doctrines, that ſwerved from, or ſuited not the Scripture dialect. He kept cloſe to the Analogy of Faith; yet was not againſt profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, or a modeſt improvement of knowledge: Yea, he had well ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the <hi>Arminian</hi> Controverſy, and told ſome Friends, That if the Lord ſhould recover him, and lengthen out his Life, he had a deſign to write ſomething upon that Subject, which might, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, have given further light into that Controverſie. For as his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius led him that way, ſo he had the advantage of many years inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate converſe with that Ancient and Learned Divine Mr. <hi>Tho. John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Halſall,</hi> a man of vaſt Parts, and unwearied Studies,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:103239:55"/> and a non ſuch Perſon in thoſe points; but told Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> (his intimate Friend) that it much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him, that he had ſpent ſo much time in reading Books, and ſtudying Controverſies, that might have been more profitably impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in converſing with, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his ignorant and carnal Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. Let Miniſters think of this, for one Soul won to God by perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conference, will tend more to God's Glory, and a Miniſter's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, than a thouſand Notions got by reading: Howbeit, a due mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a contemplative, and active Life, muſt needs be the beſt.</p>
            <p n="16">16. He was good in his Relative Condition. He was an obedient Child, an exceeding kind Husband, an indulgent tender-hearted Father, an affectionate Maſter, a faithful Friend: He maintained a Paternal awe, authority, gravity, mixed with Fatherly Bowels of gentleneſs and lenity, and both with incredible
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:103239:55"/> prudence, that they had not occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion either to ſlight him, or be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by him. He inſtructed them with faithfulneſs; admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with tenderneſs; prayed for them with faith and fervency, and walkt before them with an holy exemplarineſs and ſincerity. As God had made him a <hi>Nathanael,</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; ſo a <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> reſolving that <note place="margin">Joſh. 24. 15.</note> 
               <hi>he and his houſe ſhould ſerve the Lord.</hi> It's a true Maxim, That he who is not relatively good, is not really good: But he ſtood ſquare for every Duty in every Relation: He kept his Children much at home, being very jealous leſt they ſhould meet with temptations abroad, which occaſioned many Cares and Prayers about their diſpoſal.</p>
            <p n="17">17. He had attained to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable meaſure of Aſſurance: Tho <note place="margin">Iſa. 50. 10.</note> he had walked in darkneſs, and ſaw no light in his firſt Convictions; yet ſtaying himſelf on the Lord, his God at laſt ſhined upon his Soul
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:103239:56"/> with the light of his countenance, and he walked many days with the Candle of God ſhining upon his head through much darkneſs. How <note place="margin">Job 29. 3.</note> frequently in Prayer did he expreſs his joy and gratitude for the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting conſolation and good hopes through grace of his own ſalvation! But the infinitely wiſe God, after many ſweet days he had enjoyed, thought fit to withdraw his wonted Incomes, and left him under ſome doubts and diſſatisfaction. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two months before he died, one Lord's day, as he and his Family ſate together, he told his Wife with tears in his eyes, that he had great troubles concerning his Spiritual State, and ſome doubts about his Condition, deſiring her to pray for him: Yet the Lord diſpelled thoſe dark Clouds, and in due time did ſweetly ſhine into his Soul with the ſenſe of his Love. Thus God is a free Agent, and doth not always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail comfort upon ſincerity; but
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:103239:56"/> ſometimes the beſt of God's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſuffer Eclipſes; but ſuch ſad days tend to ſelf-ſearching and deeper humiliation; and ſuch ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings tend to better ſettlement: Yea ſuch diſcouragements are often attended with more inlargement; ſuch blots in a Chriſtian's Evidences produce more clearing them up: However, God hereby hath more glory, and Heaven will be ſweeter.</p>
            <p n="18">18. He had a ſtrong perſuaſion of God's care of his numerous Family, both in point of Education and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. As God had graciouſly lookt after them in his life-time, ſo he had conceived great hopes of their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply after his deceaſe. It's true, he had ſome temptations, and ſad thoughts of heart concerning them; but at laſt Faith got the victory over Unbelief, and having left his ſad Widow with her better Husband, and his fatherleſs Children with their heavenly Father, he was quiet, and theſe thoughts did not hinder
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:103239:57"/> his hearty welcome of his deareſt Lord, when he ſummoned him by death. And therefore after he had by faith and prayer devolved the care of them upon the Lord, he freely acquieſced in his good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence about himſelf and them. On <hi>Tueſday</hi> before he died, getting into his Bed, his Wind being very ſhort, his Wife broke out into ſore weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; to whom he ſaid, Be not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, God will provide neceſſaries for thee and thy Poſterity for ever: Which brings to mind the paſſage of <hi>Bucer,</hi> who dying, ſtretched out three Fingers, with his eyes lift up to Heaven, ſaying, <hi>[Ille, ille regit &amp; moderatur omnia;] He, he alone, rules and governs all things:</hi> And the Event hath abundantly anſwered this good man's Prediction, and Expectation.</p>
            <p n="19">19. It is very conſiderable that he had his deſire in a leiſurely lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring death: He had often expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his willingneſs (if that were
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:103239:57"/> God's will) that death might come on gradually, and not ſurprize him; yea he prayed that he might be long in his ſickneſs, and alſo that he might be ſenſible till the laſt; the Lord did condeſcend to him in both theſe: He had been long habitual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared, but he deſired to be actually ready: For it is an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant concern to dye, and go into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, a world of Spirits. This good man had frequent warnings, and continued ſtrong in his Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals all the time of his illneſs. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Friday</hi> night his Brother-in-law coming to him, asked him if he had made his Will; he anſwered, no; he deſired to have his Son <hi>Nathanael</hi> at home, when he did that: But he perceiving that he was weakning apace, and that his time would not be long, being urged again, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly conſented, and ſent for a Clerk, and diſpatcht that worldly concern that night; then he was in perfect compoſedneſs of mind, being
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:103239:58"/> but one night beſides that till his death.</p>
            <p n="20">20. As he was highly qualified with Perſonal Diſpoſition, Chriſtian Graces, and Miniſterial Abilities, ſo God gave him favour in the ſight of all with whom he converſed: It's true, he had Adverſaries, but it was for the matters of his God, wherein his Principles carried him to practices different from them; yet even thoſe commended him for his Parts and Preaching: Yea at death, ſome that had been bitter Enemies to him, were well recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to him. One inſtance was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable; one Mr. <hi>Brownlow,</hi> an old Gentleman that lived in the Town, who had conceived a bitter grudge againſt Mr. <hi>Heywood,</hi> after King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Return, becauſe he would not read the Common-Prayer; but upon his Death-bed he ſent for Mr. <hi>Heywood,</hi> intreated him to go to prayer with him; and when Mr. <hi>A.</hi> the Vicar would have come
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:103239:58"/> to read Common Prayer, he would not ſuffer him; but would not part with Mr. <hi>Heywood</hi> while he lived.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given a brief Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of what was memorable in this holy man of God, and imitable by us: I may ſay to every one, Go thou and do likewiſe. Let Chriſtians pray that God would ſend forth many ſuch Labourers into his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, ſucceed their Labours, and learn to improve ſuch Soul-helps, that they may give a good account of theſe rich Talents at laſt.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Letter ſent by Mr.</hi> Nathanael Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood <hi>to a Chriſtian Friend, upon the death of his godly Wife,</hi> May 1. 1675.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received yours of <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. long ſince, and had anſwered it much ſooner, but that I had ſome purpoſes, and was not without hopes, of doing it, not by writing, but by coming to you at your appointed time in <hi>March</hi> laſt; but being prevented of that, and now having ſuch pains of body, through my old diſtemper, as makes me very uncapable of riding far, that I am not certain to ſee you this Summer, though I intend and ſhall endeavour it; I can forbear writing no longer, nor further delay that which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:103239:59"/> I account my duty, till I come over, I give you hearty thanks for your loving and godly Letter; whereby I was much refreſhed in thoſe my late troubles, which indeed were many and heavy; yet in ſuch a Cauſe, and for ſuch a Maſter, did I ſuffer, that I muſt needs ſay they were light and eaſy: Oh! that God may have the glory, and others be encouraged! As ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Chriſt did abound, ſo conſolations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded by Chriſt. Let the world know that ſuffering for Chriſt is the very Element wherein Chriſt's Love liveth and exerciſeth it ſelf, and his choiceſt Cordials are reſerved for ſuch a time. I was in great meaſure a ſtranger to the comforts and ſweetneſs of Chriſtianity, till I was ſingled out to bear the Croſs; but am now well ſatisfied that that which I ſuffered for, and ſtill do ſuffer, is Chriſt's Truth; becauſe he was pleaſed to ſeal my ſufferings with the ſweet ſenſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of unſpeakable joy and peace; and I know he will not put his ſeal to a blank-paper, nor will he be a witneſs to a lye. Had not ſome great Perſons interpoſed by their Intereſt and Authority, I had certainly gone to Priſon at that time, when I was taken by Soldiers; and at the Seſſions ſhortly after, had not God raiſed up other Friends (ſome of them Juſtices) to fruſtrate the purpoſe and deſign of my cruel Enemies, who would have ſent me Six Months to Priſon the Seſſions before, for living within Five Miles of this Town; yea, would have Convicted me among Recuſants for not coming to this Church; but it pleaſed God, by a ſpecial Providence, to prevent that alſo. But alas! all theſe troubles are nothing to that I am now Mourning under, the loſs of publick Liberty; a cloſed Mouth, dumb and ſilent Sabbaths; to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:103239:59"/> be caſt out of the Vineyard as a dry and wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Branch, and to be laid aſide as a broken Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, in whom there is no pleaſure, is a ſore bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, I know not how to bear; my heart bleeds under it, as a ſting and edge added to my other troubles and afflictions. This exerciſe of my Miniſtry, next to Chriſt, is dearer to me than any thing in the world: It was my Heaven, till I come home, even to ſpend this life in gathering Souls to Chriſt: But I muſt lay even that down at Chriſt's feet, and be dumb and ſilent before the Lord, becauſe he has done it, who can do no wrong, and whoſe judgments are paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out: I am ſure I have reaſon to conclude with the Prophet, <hi>I will bear the indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dear Brother;</p>
               <p>I hear that it hath pleaſed God to remove from you the deſire of your eyes, and my dear Friend: I am heartily ſorry for that ſore breach in your Family, and deſire to ſuffer with you in the loſs of your loving and good Wife, now gone before (according to the method and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he hath appointed, whoſe Underſtanding is infinite) whither you are ſhortly to follow: He that made yeſterday to go before this day, and the former Generation in birth and life to have been before this Generation, and hath made ſome Flowers grow, ſo to die and wither in <hi>May,</hi> and others in <hi>June,</hi> cannot be challenged in the order he obſerves with us, that one muſt bury another. You know who ſaid, <hi>I was dumb and opened not my mouth, becauſe thou, Lord, didſt it.</hi> All things are Ordered in Wiſdom and Judgment by your Father; at whoſe feet your own Soul and your Heaven lyeth, and ſo the days of your Wife. You had her as long as
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:103239:60"/> your Leaſe laſted, and ſeeing her Term was come, and your Leaſe run out, you can no more juſtly quarrel with the great Sovereign for taking his own at his juſt Term-day, than a poor Farmer can complain that his Maſter takes a portion of his own Land to himſelf when his Leaſe is expired: And is not he an ill debtor who payeth that which he hath borrowed with a grudg? Certainly the long loan of ſuch a good Wife, an Heir of Grace, and Member of Chriſt (as I verily believe) deſerveth more thanks, at the Creditors hands, than that you ſhould grieve and murmur when he craveth but his own. I believe you would judge them to be but unthankful Neighbours who would pay you a ſum of Money after this manner. I know you would be ſorry either to be, or to be eſteemed any thing like an Atheiſt; and yet not I, but the Apoſtle (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 13.) thinks thoſe to be hopeleſs Atheiſts, who Mourn exceſſively for the Dead. But this is not a challenge on my part; ſome jealouſie I have, leſt you be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much grieved for the loſs of ſuch a meet-Help; but you have reaſon to rejoyce, that when a part of you is on Earth, another part of you is Glorified in Heaven, ſleeping in the Boſom of the Almighty: Fellow her, but envy her not. For indeed it is ſelf-love in us that maketh us Mourn for them that die in the Lord; becauſe for them we cannot Mourn, ſince they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happy till they be dead, therefore we Mourn for our own private reſpect. Take heed then, that in pretending your affection in Mourning for your Wife, you act out of ſelf-affection; conſider what the Lord is doing in it; ſhe is plucked out of the fire, and reſteth from her Labours; and the Lord in that is trying you,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:103239:60"/> and caſting you into the fire, beholding your Faith and Patience, and delighting to ſee you in the burning Buſh and not conſumed; but ſending Satan away fruſtrate of his deſign. The Lord is laying in the two ſcales of the Ballance, your making Conſcience of Submiſſion to his Gracious Will; and in the other, your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your Wife: Which of the two will you then chuſe to ſatisfy? I wiſh you may come out of the Lord's School wiſer and more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in the ways of God. It's our happineſs that when Chriſt openeth a Vein, he taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ill Blood from his ſick Patients; and when he puts them into the furnace of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (and ſtands by the melting of the Mettal) he takes away the tin and lead, and ſcum that remained in nature. But it is a ſad thing when the rod is curſed, that never fruit ſhall grow on it; and except Chriſt's dew fall down his Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sunſhine, and his Grace follow Afflictions, to make them to bring forth fruit unto God, they are ſo bewithered to us, that our evil ground (rank and fat enough for Briars) caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up a crop of noyſome Weeds. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded your Loſſes, Cares, Sickneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are but Summer-ſhowres that will wet your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for an hour or two, and the Sun of the New Jeruſalem ſhall quickly dry your wet Coat, eſpecially ſince the rain of affliction can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtain the Image of God, nor cauſe Grace to caſt it's Colour. Oh! learn heavenly Wiſdom, Self-denial, and Mortification, by this ſad loſs. I know it is not for nothing (except you deny God to be Wiſe in all that he doth) that you have loſt one in the Earth: It may be there hath been too little of your heart and love in Heaven; and therefore the jealouſie of Chriſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:103239:61"/> hath done this; it's a mercy that he contendeth with you, and your Lovers; it may be he hath either been out of his place, or in a place infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to his worth. O let Chriſt have the room of your Wife; ſhe hath now no need of you, or your Love; ſhe enjoyeth as much of the love of Chriſt, as her heart can be capable of. I know it is a dear bought experience to teach you to undervalue the Creature; yet it is not too dear if Chriſt think ſo. Let me entreat you to conſider one thing more (which hath help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in ſuch like caſes more than once) and I have done: You are haſting after your Wife, and ſhall ſhortly be with her; it's but a little while, a few days longer, and you muſt follow her into Eternity. By her Death take occaſion to love the world leſs, out of which ſhe is taken, and Heaven more, whither ſhe is gone before you, and where you ſhall for ever enjoy her, and be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all. If the place ſhe hath left were any other but a priſon of Sin, and the home ſhe is gone to were any other but a Palace of Glory, your Grief would be the more rational. But, I hope, your Faith of the Reſurrection of the dead in Chriſt to Glory and Immortality, will lead you to dry up your Tears, and ſuſpend your longing for her, till the Morning of that Day, when the Arch-Angel ſhall deſcend with a ſhout to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his Priſoners out of their Graves up to himſelf in Heaven.—Dear love to, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers for you and your Children. I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your most Affectionate and Sympathyſing Friend,</hi> Nath. Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
